<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sinne kept out of the kingdome</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N317A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833849</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833849</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38327</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38327)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2213:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sinne kept out of the kingdome</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at foot: James Nailer.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Copy cut and pasted onto 4 leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:38327:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Sinne kept out of the Kingdome.</head>
            <p>ALL Profeſſors and People conſider where you are, and from whence you are fallen, you that plead <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſay none can be ſet free from ſin while they are in the world, you plead for a Hold for Satan in you while you are here, and where will you have him caſt out, or what fellowſhip can you have with God ſo long as the Serpent is Head in you?<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.3.</note> you are ſeperated from God, and knows him not; for what communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath light with darkneſſe?<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14</note> God is light, and he that dwels in God dwels in light, and in him is no darkneſſe at all: but while you live in ſin, you are in darkneſſe, and the god of this world hath blinded your eyes that you cannot ſee it;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> you are led captive at his will to ſerve him, and you are willing to be ſo, and you do not beleeve that ever you ſhall be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: you are ſervants to ſin, and you take pleaſure in it you are in the fleſh and ſin, and have made a covenant with Hell, and darkneſſe, and death: You are reſolved to ſerve and pleaſe the fleſh while you live, and you will repent at your death; you have forgot that your times are in the Hand of the Lord,<note place="margin">Heb 3.7, 8</note> and that this is the day of grace and repentance, which you turn into laſciviouſneſſe and wantonneſſe, you make it plainly appear, you have your luſtfull pleaſures, wantonneſſe, and filthineſſe, and love them more then God: You that love the world and the things of the world, the love of the Father is not in you;<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.15 and 16.</note> for whom you love, him will you follow. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If you love me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>keep my commands,</hi> and thoſe that follow him, he leads them out of all the wayes of ſin, into the wayes of puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and holineſſe,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.19.</note> and ſo he is the way to the father; <hi>For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe none can ever ſee God, for he is of purer eyes then to behold iniquitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>neither can any unclean thing come in his ſight:</hi> But while you are following the Prince of the Aire, which ruleth in the Children of diſobedience, bringing forth fruits of ſinne and unrighteouſneſſe, having your converſation in the earth, and earthly things, following your corrupt wills and pleaſures, an<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:38327:2"/>yet you will profeſſe you love God, and own him in words, and the Devill in practice: Oh horrible hypocriſie! ſhall not the righteous God finde you out, and reward you according to your works;<note place="margin">Mat. 16.27</note> you cannot deceive him, you deceive your ſelves who think to be Heirs of two Kingdoms, you will have the pleaſures of ſin here, and you ſay you hope to be Heirs of the Kingdome of Heaven too; but the hope of the Hypocrite ſhall periſh; remember thy father <hi>Dives,</hi> in whoſe ſteps thou walk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt, and the ſame way leads to the ſame end. The Lord ſaith that <hi>the wicked ſhall be turned into Hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.17.</note> 
               <hi>and all that forgets God</hi> But the deceit in thee ſayes, That thou maiſt live in ſinne while thou art here, and have thy thoughts in the world, and yet thou ſhalt enter into the Kingdome of Heaven too: Now who muſt be the Lyar, whether God or thou, O vain man? was it not ſin that ſeparated God and man at the firſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> and thinke thou to be reconciled again ſo long as ſin ſtands in thee? Ma<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> was not created in ſin,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.19, 20,—</note> but pure and holy, in the Image of God and while he ſtood here he had communion with God,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> and ha<gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the pure wiſdome of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.17.</note> by which he was able to ſee into the wonders of God, and to give Names unto all Creatures; but ſo ſoon as he had committed ſin, he was ſtript of all this, and became naked, and was thruſt out of Paradice, and was curſe from the Lord, yea the ground was curſed for his ſake; and all this becauſe of ſin which thou thinkeſt ſo light of: for odious is ſin in the pure eyes of the Holy God, and didſt thou but know thy condition as thou lyeſt in ſin, in thy firſt birth a Child of wrath, and one to whom all the Curſes in the Book of God are due, thou wouldeſt tremble at ſinne, and not plead for it wherein thou plainly ſheweſt thy ſelf to be the ſervant of the Devill. And when thou thus abuſeſt the goodneſſ of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to the 11.</note> that having left the failings of others upon Record as warnings to all that come after not to doe the like, and theſe thou makeſt uſe of to incourage thee in thy ſin and filthi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:38327:2"/>and becauſe God is mercifull to pardon ſinners at what time ſoever they repent, therefore thou art incouraged to live in ſin the longer, unrepented of. Now all that have eyes in their heads may plainly ſee whoſe Child thou art: for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Know ye not that the long-ſuffering of God, and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leads to repentance;</hi> it doth ſo to the Children of God;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> but that Scripture is fulfilled in thee, which ſaith,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſpeedily executed on the wicked, therefore his heart is ſet in him to do wickedneſse:</hi> and thus thou makeſt the mercy of God a Cloak for thy unrighteous actions, and yet thou wilt talk of a Redeemer, and of faith in Chriſt; but (O friend) where is thy Redeemer witneſſed, while thou art yet in thy ſins? what art thou redeemed from, or what art thou redeemed to? thoſe that are redeemed are ſet free from the ſevitude of ſin,<note place="margin">Iohn 8.24, 25, 26.</note> but thou ſerveſt ſinne ſo long as thou obeyeſt the motions of it; then where is thy freedome? Canſt thou witneſſe Chriſt dyed for thee, and thy ſins ſtill alive? how wilt thou witneſſe his death in thee, or thy ſelf dead with him? the Saints that were dead with Chriſt, were dead to ſin;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.2.</note> and (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>How can you that are dead to ſinne, live any longer therein?</hi> and ſaith alſo, <hi>Thoſe that are dead with Chriſt are free from ſin, and are become ſervants of righteouſneſſe:</hi> again he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.22, 23,—</note> 
               <hi>Now being made free from ſin, and become ſervants of God, ye have your fruits unto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſse, and the end thereof eternall life.</hi> But while thou liveſt in ſin, thy fruits are unholy, and the end thereof is death; and then where is thy redemption? They who are redeemed by Chriſt, are redeemed from earth and earthly things,<note place="margin">Revel. 5.9, 10,—</note> unto God again, from whence they had fallen, out of every Tongue Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, People and Nation, and are made unto God Kings and Preiſts, to reign above ſin on the earth, and are made confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to his Image again, which was loſt by ſin: but what conformitie is there in thee, while thou art in ſin, thou art not like him, but like the Devill; for every ſin is the image of the
<pb facs="tcp:38327:3"/>Devill, who ſinned from the beginning; and while thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteſt ſin, thou holdeſt forth the image of the Devill in thee, who is thy father: and Chriſt told the Scribes and Phariſees,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> who profeſſed to be the Children of God, but lived in ſin, that they were of their father the Devill, for his works they would do; for every ſin is the work of the Devill;<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> and (ſaith <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>He that commits ſin, is of the Devill;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>For this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was the Son of God manifeſted to deſtroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> Whoſoever can witneſſe Chriſt manifeſted in them, can witneſſe ſin deſtroyed; but if thou ſay thou canſt witneſſe Chriſt manifeſt in thee, and yet commit ſin, thou art a Lyar: for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>whoſoever abideth in him, ſinneth not whoſoever ſinneth hath not ſeen him, neither known him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſaith he knows him and keepeth not his commandements, is a Lyar, and the truth is not in him:</hi> and ſaith the holy Ghoſt <hi>whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.4.</note> but he that is begotten of God keepeth himſelf and the wicked one toucheth him not;</hi> and ſaith again, that <hi>whoſoever is born of God ſinneth not, for his ſeed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10,—</note> and ſaith plainly, <hi>In this are the Children of God manifeſt, and the Children of the Devill, whoſoever doth not righteouſneſse, is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 13.14.</note> God in all ages hath known his by their obedience, but thou ſayeſt thou mayeſt live in diſobedience, and yet bee counted one of his too; but where is thy Mark by which thou art known from the world? thoſe that are Gods are marked and known from the world;<note place="margin">Rev. 7.3.4.</note> but thou art in love with the world, and canſt conform with them in all their wayes, words, works, and worſhips,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.4.</note> and yet would be counted one of Gods too. O thou deceiver, thou deceiveſt but thy ſelf and men that are like thee, for thou canſt not deceive the Lord. Tike heed, repent, halt no longer between God and the world; if thou wouldeſt own <hi>GOD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.1<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> thou muſt diſown the world, and the world will diſown thee; thou cauſt not have both.</p>
            <byline>
               <hi>Written by</hi> James Nailer, <hi>late priſoner in Appleby Caſtle, by the dark world called a Quaker.</hi>
            </byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
